A Guide to the Stanford E. Chaillé Collection, 1860-1903
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Stanford E. Chaillé Collection, 1860-1903
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2008-031
1 box; 0.2 cu. ft.
Letters, government issued documents, printed material, and two photo albums of Dr. Stanford E. Chaillé, Confederate surgeon and dean of Tulane University's medical school. Significant topics include the Union occupation of New Orleans, postwar elections, Dr. Chaillé's medical career, and Chaillé genealogy. Materials cover the period shortly before the Civil War to the early twentieth century, and deal mostly with New Orleans.
Dr. Stanford E. Chaillé
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Stanford E. Chaillé Collection was purchased by Special Collections in 2004.
Biographical Information
Stanford E. Chaillé was born on July 9, 1830, in Natchez, Mississippi, the descendant of several patriots of the Revolutionary War. Educated by private tutors until his mother's death, Chaillé eventually graduated from Phillips' Academy in South Andover, Massachusetts, in 1847. Chaillé then received an A. B. (bachelor's degree) in 1851 from Harvard College and later earned his medical degree from the Medical Department of the University of Louisiana (now Tulane) in 1853. Chaillé later returned to Harvard College and received an A. M. (master's degree) in 1854. On February 23, 1857, Dr. Chaillé married Laura E. Montfort. The union produced one child, Mary Laura Chaillé. Laura E. Montfort died on August 18, 1858. Before the Civil War, Dr. Chaillé worked as a resident student in the New Orleans Charity Hospital and then served as a resident physician at the United States Marine Hospital and at the Circus Street Infirmary.
During the war, Dr. Chaillé rose from being a private in the New Orleans Light Horse Brigade to acting Confederate Surgeon General of Louisiana in 1862. In May, 1862, Dr. Chaillé became the surgeon and medical inspector of the Confederate Army of Tennessee. In July of 1863, Dr. Chaillé took the post of surgeon-in-charge of the Fairground Hospital #2 in Atlanta, Georgia, then transferred to Okmulgee Hospital in Macon, Georgia in December, 1863. While in Georgia, Dr. Chaillé met, and later married, Mary Louisa Napier.
After the Civil War, Dr. Chaillé lectured and demonstrated anatomy and obstetrics in New Orleans. In 1878, Congress selected Dr. Chaillé to study the great yellow fever epidemic, and he later sat on the Havana Yellow Fever Commission. Dr. Chaillé also contributed significantly to medical literature. Among these contributions was his formulation of infant developmental standards in 1887. From 1885 until his retirement in 1908, Dr. Chaillé served as the dean of Tulane's medical school. Dr. Stanford E. Chaillé died in 1911.
Scope and Content
The Stanford E. Chaillé Collection consists of letters, government-issued documents, printed material, and two photo albums containing thirty-six photos. Those pictured in photos include: Dr. Chaillé, Laura Chaillé, Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Layton M. D. P., and other friends. Materials date from shortly before the American Civil War to the decades following southern Reconstruction. Salient topics are the occupation of New Orleans by the Union during the Civil War, postwar government elections, the great yellow fever epidemic, and Dr. Chaillé's long career and accolades. Several documents relate to Dr. Chaillé's position as dean of the Tulane Medical School, such as a notable graduation speech welcoming Confederate leader Jefferson Davis. Dr. Chaillé's interest in genealogical research also appears in letters and documents. In one genealogical sketch, Dr. Chaillé traces his family tree to France where it was "very Catholic" before 1540.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type. Letters appear chronologically.
Contents List
- Stanford E. Chaillé's biographical/genealogical information, 1863-1899 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Confederate marriage license for Stanford E. Chaillé and Mary L. Napier, 1863
  - Biographical Sketch of Dr. Chaillé, 1894
  - Manuscript resume, 1899
  - Manuscript of Chaillé lineage, 1899
- Correspondence 1862-1903 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Letter from Mr. Legaré, Farmington, April 30, 1862
    Discusses Mr. Legaré's travels through Union held New Orleans and Baton Rouge.
  - Letter from A.L.N., New Orleans, LA, May 14, 1862
    Advises Dr. Chaillé to return to New Orleans.
  - Letter from Henry Hacksford, New Orleans, LA, May 17, 1862
    Advises Dr. Chaillé to return to the city.
  - Letter from Mary Owen Preston, Lexington, October 5, 1862
    Discusses the confederate evacuation of Lexington and includes a picture of Mrs. William Preston and Caroline Preston.
  - Letter from Marvin T. Myers, Richmond, October 12, 1862
    Discusses fight at Leesburg with Lee.
  - Letter from Stanford E. Chaillé to a Mr. Barker, New Orleans, LA, March 22, 1883
    Requests a copy of the Medical News and apologizes for previous abruptness.
  - Letter from Mr. Legaré, Mobile, April 20, 1864
    Discusses a Confederate coward.
  - Letter from Henry R. Rand, Macon, GA, February 4, 1865
    Mr. Rand admits to defrauding Dr. Chaillé of $744 but pleads for leniency
  - Letter from General Randall L. Gibson, Washington, D.C., December 25, 1876
    Asks Dr. Chaillé to analyze the Republican officers and returns board from a recent election. This letter apparently refers to Republican attempts to shut out former Confederate Democrats from power in Louisiana (postmarked envelope included).
  - Letter from W.R. Morrison, St Charles Hotel, New Orleans, LA, July 8, 1877
    Informs Dr. Chaillé of when his testimony is required (for an apparent congressional hearing).
  - Letter from the Honorable Alexander Randall, Annapolis, MD, October 31, 1877
    Informs Dr. Chaillé of the results of Alexander Randall's investigation of any person named "Peter Chaillé" in the eastern shores of Maryland.
  - Letter from Stanford E. Chaillé to Colonel Charles Chaillé Long, Asheville, NC, October 15, 1889
    Discusses Chaillé family lineage. Includes many specific questions about the Chaillé family.
  - Letter from Stanford E. Chaillé to Professor Albert B Miles, M.D., New Orleans, LA, 1894
    Letter of recommendation for Dr. Warren Stowe.
  - Letter from Alcée Fortier, New Orleans, LA, November 1, 1899
    Describes the origins of the name "Chaillé." According to Alcée Fortier, Chaillé derives from the French word for flint.
  - Letter from J. W. Nicholson, Baton Rouge, LA, June 11, 1903
    Thanks Dr. Chaillé for two addresses.
- Speech, 1889 (Box-folder 1:3)
  In this speech, Chaillé states that there is "no heart nobler and no hands braver than those of Jefferson Davis."
- Miscellaneous printed material (broadside, newspaper clipping), 1885, n.d. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Photo album 1, 1860-1880 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Photo album 2, 1866-1882 (Box-folder 1:6)